I bring to you
إنني أحضر إليكم
a message from
رسالة من
tens of thousands of people --
عشرات الألوف من الناس،
in the villages, in the slums,
في القرى والعشوائيات
in the hinterland of the country --
في المناطق النائية من البلاد،
who have solved problems
الذين حلوا مشاكلهم
through their own genius,
عبر عبقريتهم هم،
without any
بدون الحصول على
outside help.
مساعدة خارجية.
When our home minister announces
عندما أعلن وزير الإسكان عندنا
a few weeks ago
منذ عدة أسابيع
a war on
حربًا على
one third of India,
ثلث الهند،
about 200 districts that he mentioned
على أكثر من 200 منطقة ذكر أن
were ungovernable,
الحكم فيها غير مستتب
he missed the point.
فاتته نقطة ما،
The point that we have been stressing
وهي النقطة التي كنا نؤكد عليها
for the last 21 years,
طوال الواحد وعشرين سنة الأخيرة،
the point that
النقطة هي أن الناس
people may be economically poor,
قد يكونوا فقراء اقتصاديًا
but they're not poor in the mind.
ولكن عقولهم ليست بفقيرة.
In other words,
بمعنى آخر،
the minds on the margin
إن العقول المهمشة
are not the marginal minds.
ليست هي العقول الهامشية "التالفة".
That is the message,
هذه هي الرسالة،
which we started 31 years ago.
التي بدأنا بها منذ 31 عامًا.
And what did it start?
وماذا بدأت؟
Let me just tell you, briefly, my personal journey,
دعوني أقص عليكم، باختصار، رحلتي الشخصية،
which led me to come to this point.
والتي قادتني إلى هذه النقطة.
In '85, '86, I was in Bangladesh
خلال عامي85 و86 كنت في بنجلاديش
advising the government and the research council there
كمستشار للحكومة ومجلس الأبحاث هناك
how to help scientists work on the lands,
كيف نساعد العلماء ليعملوا
on the fields of the poor people,
في حقول الفقراء
and how to develop research technologies,
وكيف ننمي تقنيات بحث علمي
which are based on the knowledge of the people.
مبنية على المعرفة الموجودة لدى الناس.
I came back in '86.
وعدت في سنة 86
I had been tremendously invigorated
وكنت مدفوعًا بشكل كبير
by the knowledge and creativity that I found in that country,
بالمعرفة والإبداع اللذين وجدتهما في ذلك البلد
which had 60 percent landlessness
والذي 60 % من شعبه لا يملكون الأرض
but amazing creativity.
ولكنهم يملكون إبداعا مذهلا.
I started looking at my own work:
بدأت أنظر في عملي
The work that I had done
العمل الذي قمت به
for the previous 10 years,
خلال العشر سنوات الماضية،
almost every time,
تقريبًا في كل مرة،
had instances of knowledge
كان هناك نماذج من المعرفة
that people had shared.
التي أطلعني الناس عليها.
Now, I was paid in dollars as a consultant,
والآن، أنا أتقاضى راتبي بالدولار، كمستشار،
and I looked at my income tax return
ونظرت إلى بيان ضريبة الدخل الخاص بي
and tried to ask myself: "Is there a line in my return,
وحاولت أن أسأل نفسي: "هل هناك سطر معين في هذا البيان،
which shows how much of this income has gone
يبين كم من هذا الدخل ذهب
to the people whose knowledge
إلى الناس الذين بفضل معرفتهم التي أعطوني إياها
has made it possible?
أصبح وجود هذا الدخل ممكنًا؟
Was it because I'm brilliant
هل هذا لأني عبقري
that I'm getting this reward, or because of the revolution?
هل لهذا آخذ هذا الراتب، أو .........؟
Is it that I write very well?
هل بسبب أنني أكتب جيدًا؟
Is it that I articulate very well?
هل بسبب أنني أتحدث جيدًا؟
Is it that I analyze the data very well?
هل بسبب أنني أحلل البيانات جيدًا؟
Is it because I'm a professor, and, therefore,
هل بسبب أنني أستاذ جامعي، وبالتالي
I must be entitled to this reward from society?"
فأنا مستحق لهذه المكافأة من المجتمع؟
I tried to convince myself that, "No, no,
وحاولت أن أقنع نفسي أنه، "لا، لا،
I have worked for the policy changes.
لقد بذلت جهدا لتغيير السياسات.
You know, the public policy will become
كما تعرفون، أن السياسة العامة سوف تصبح
more responsive to the needs of the poor,
أكثر استجابة لاحتياجات الفقراء،
and, therefore I think it's okay."
وبالتالي، أظن أن الأمر على ما يرام."
But it appeared to me
ولكن خطر لي
that all these years that I'd been working on exploitation --
أن كل هذه السنوات التي أمضيتها أحارب الاستغلال
exploitation by landlords,
استغلال أصحاب الأراضي،
by moneylenders, by traders --
والمقرضين، والتجار،
gave me an insight that
لفتت انتباهي إلى
probably I was also an exploiter,
أنه من الممكن أن أكون أنا أيضًا مستغل،
because there was no line in my income tax return
لأنه لا يوجد سطر معين في بيان ضريبة الدخل الخاص بي
which showed this income accrued
يوضح أن هذا الدخل حدث
because of the brilliance of the people --
بسبب عبقرية الناس،
those people who have shared their knowledge and good faith and trust with me --
هؤلاء الناس الذين أودعوني معرفتهم وإيمانهم وثقتهم،
and nothing ever went back to them.
ولم ينالهم من هذا شئ.
So much so, that much of my work till that time
لدرجة أنه حتى ذلك الوقت كل أعمالي
was in the English language.
كانت مكتوبة باللغة الإنجليزية.
The majority of the people from whom I learned didn't know English.
أغلبية الناس الذين تعلمت منهم لم يتكلموا الإنجليزية
So what kind of a contributor was I?
لذا فأي نوع من المشاركين كنت أنا؟
I was talking about social justice,
كنت أتحدث عن العدالة الاجتماعية،
and here I was, a professional
ولكني كنت في نفس الوقت
who was pursuing the most unjust act --
أمارس أكثر الأعمال ظلمًا
of taking knowledge from the people, making them anonymous,
بأن آخذ المعرفة من الناس، ثم لا أذكرهم،
getting rent from that knowledge
أصبح ثريًأ بسبب هذه المعرفة
by sharing it and doing consultancy, writing papers and
عن طريق مشاركتها مع الآخرين، وعمل الاستشارات، وكتابة الأبحاث،
publishing them in the papers,
ونشر هذه الأبحاث،
getting invited to the conferences,
وأدعى إلى المؤتمرات،
getting consultancies and whatever have you.
وأحصل على استشارات، وكل ما يتبادر إلى عقولكم.
So then, a dilemma rose in the mind that,
ثم، انتبهت إلى مشكلة،
if I'm also an exploiter, then this is not right;
أنه إذا كنت أنا أيضًا مستغلًا، فهذا ليس صوابًا؛
life cannot go on like that.
لا يمكن أن تستمر الحياة بهذا الشكل.
And this was a moment of great pain and trauma
وكانت هذه لحظة من الألم والصدمة
because I couldn't live with it any longer.
لأنني لم أعد استطيع التعايش مع هذا الوضع أكثر من ذلك.
So I did a review of
ولهذا كتبت مقالة عن،
ethical dilemma and value conflicts and management research,
تضارب القيم والإشكاليات الأخلاقية في العلوم الاجتماعيات وأبحاث الإدارة،
wrote, read about 100 papers.
وكتبت وقرأت حوالي 100 ورقة علمية.
And I came to the conclusion that
وتوصلت إلى استنتاج،
while dilemma is unique,
على الرغم من غرابة المعضلة،
dilemma is not unique; the solution had to be unique.
إن المعضلة ليست غريبة، إنه الحل هو الذي لابد أن يكون غريبًا.
And one day -- I don't know what happened --
وفي يوم من الأيام -- لا أعلم ما الذي حدث --
while coming back from the office towards home,
عندما كنت عائدًا من المكتب إلى المنزل،
maybe I saw a honey bee
ربما أكون رأيت نحلة من نحلات العسل،
or it occurred to my mind that if I only could be like the honey bee,
أو أنه قد خطر لي أنه إذا استطعت أن أكون مثل النحلة،
life would be wonderful.
سوف تكون الحياة رائعة.
What the honey bee does: it pollinates,
فالذي تفعله نحلات العسل هو: أن تدخل ابرتها في وردة،
takes nectar from the flower,
ثم تمتص الرحيق من هذه الوردة،
pollinates another flower, cross-pollinates.
ثم تدخل ابرتها في وردة أخرى، وهكذا.
And when it takes the nectar,
وعندما تمتص الرحيق،
the flowers don't feel shortchanged.
لا تشعر الوردة بالنقص ولا بفقدان هذا الرحيق.
In fact, they invite the honey bees
بل في الحقيقة، الورود تدعوا نحلات العسل
through their colors,
من خلال ألوانها.
and the bees don't keep all the honey for themselves.
ولا تحتفظ النحلات بكل العسل لأنفسها.
These are the three guiding principles of the Honey Bee Network:
هذه هي المبادئ الثلاثة الرئيسية التي تحكم شبكة نحلات العسل --
that whenever we learn something from people
أنه عندما نتعلم شيئًا ما من الناس
it must be shared with them in their language.
لابد من مشاركته معهم بلغتهم.
They must not remain anonymous.
ويجب أن لا يظلوا مجهولين.
And I must tell you that after 20 years,
ولابد أن أخبركم أنه بعد 20 سنة،
I have not made one percent of change
لم استطع تغيير حتى واحد بالمائة
in the professional practice of this art.
من الممارسة المهنية لهذه المهنة.
That is a great tragedy -- which I'm carrying still with me
وهذه مأساة عظمى مازلت أحملها معي حتى الآن،
and I hope that all of you will carry this with you --
وأتمنى أن تحملوها جميعًا معكم،
that the profession still legitimizes publication
أن المهنة ما زالت تسمح بنشر
of knowledge of people without attributing them
معارف الناس بدون أن تعزو إليهم هذه العلوم،
by making them anonymous.
بجعلهم مجهولين.
The research guidelines of U.S. National Academy of Sciences
مبادئ البحث العلمي الخاصة بالأكاديمية الوطنية للعلوم بالولايات المتحدة
or Research Councils of the U.K.
أو بمجالس البحث العلمي بالمملكة المتحدة،
or of Indian Councils of Science Research
أو بمجالس البحث العلمي بالهند
do not require
لا تطلب،
that whatever you learn from people, you must share back with them.
أن تشارك ما تعلمته من الناس معهم
We are talking about an accountable society,
نحن نتكلم عن مجتمع مسؤول،
a society that is fair and just,
مجتمع عادل وسوي،
and we don't even do justice in the knowledge market.
ونحن لا نطبق العدل حتى في سوق المعرفة.
And India wants to be a knowledge society.
وتريد الهند أن تكون مجتمعًا للمعرفة.
How will it be a knowledge society?
كيف لها أن تكون مثل هذا المجتمع؟
So, obviously, you cannot have two principles of justice,
وبالتالي، من الواضح، أنه لا يمكنك أن تكيل العدالة بمكيالين
one for yourself and one for others.
أحدهما تحكم به على نفسك والآخر تحكم به على الآخرين.
It must be the same.
لابد أن يكون لك مكيال واحد .
You cannot discriminate.
لا يمكن أن تفصل بين الحالتين.
You cannot be in favor of your own values,
لا يمكن أن تحابي قيمك الخاصة
which are at a distance from
والتي تبعد عن
the values that you espouse.
تلك القيم التي تناصرها أنت.
So, fairness to one and to the other
لذا، العدل بالنسبة لشخص ما أو لآخر
is not divisible.
غير قابل للقسمة.
Look at this picture.
انظر إلى الصورة.
Can you tell me where has it been taken from,
هل يمكن لأحد أن يخبرني من أين أخذت
and what is it meant for? Anybody?
وبماذا استخدمت ، هل من أحد؟
I'm a professor; I must quiz you. (Laughter)
أنا استاذ جامعي؛ لابد أن أختبركم.
Anybody? Any guess at all?
أي أحد؟ أي تخمين على الإطلاق.
Pardon? (Audience Member: Rajasthan.)
عذرًا؟ (أحد الجماهير: راجاثان)
Anil Gupta: But what has it been used for? What has it been used for?
أنيل جوبتا: ولكن ما الذي تستخدم فيه؟ ما الذي استخدمت فيه؟
(Murmuring)
(همهمة)
Pardon?
عذرًا؟
You know, you're so right. We must give him a hand,
أتعرف أنت على صواب. لابد أن نصفق له.
because this man knows how insensitive our government is.
لأن هذا الرجل يعلم كم هي حكومتنا غير حساسة.
Look at this. This is the site of the government of India.
أنظروا إلى هذا. هذا هو الموقع الإليكتروني الخاص بحكومة الهند.
It invites tourists
انه يدعو السائحين
to see the shame of our country.
ليروا عار بلادنا
I'm so sorry to say that.
أنا آسف جدًا لقولي هذا.
Is this a beautiful picture
هل هذه صورة جميلة --
or is it a terrible picture?
أم صورة مروعة؟
It depends upon how you look at the life of the people.
هذا يعتمد على كيفية نظرك إلى حياة الناس.
If this woman has to carry water on her head
إذا كانت المرأة مضطرة إلى حمل الماء على رأسها
for miles and miles and miles,
لمسافة أميال وأميال
you cannot be celebrating that.
فهذا لا يدعونا لأن نفتخر به ! .
We should be doing something about it.
بل لابد أن تفعل شيئًا بشأنه.
And let me tell you, with all the science and technology at our command,
ودعوني أخبركم، أنه بكل العلوم والتكنولوجيا التي نملكها الآن،
millions of women still carry water on their heads.
ملايين النساء مازلن يحملن الماء فوق رؤوسهن.
And we do not ask this question.
ونحن لا نسأل هذا السؤال.
You must have taken tea in the morning.
لابد أنكم شربتم الشاي في الصبح.
Think for a minute.
فكروا لدقيقة.
The leaves of the tea, plucked from the bushes;
أوراق الشاي، تقطف من الأشجار.
you know what the action is? The action is:
أنتم تعرفون كيف تقطف هذه الأوراق؟ تقطف كالآتي
The lady picks up a few leaves, puts them in the basket on the backside.
المرأة تقطف مجموعة من الأوراق، وتضعهم في سلة على ظهرها
Just do it 10 times;
حاول فعل ذلك 10 مرات فقط؛
you will realize the pain in this shoulder.
سوف تشعر بالألم في كتفك.
And she does it a few thousand times
وهي تفعل ذلك عدة آلاف من المرات
every day.
كل يوم
The rice that you ate in the lunch, and you will eat today,
الأرز الذي أكلته أنت في الغذاء، والذي ستأكله اليوم،
is transplanted by women
تمت زراعته بواسطة نساء
bending in a very awkward posture,
ينحنين في وضع حرج،
millions of them,
الملايين منهم،
every season, in the paddy season,
كل موسم، في موسم الأرز،
when they transplant paddy
عندما يزرعون الأرز
with their feet in the water.
عندما تكون أقدامهم في الماء
And feet in the water will develop fungus,
ووضع الأقدام في الماء يسبب ظهور الفطريات
infections,
والإلتهابات
and that infection pains
وهذه الالتهابات تؤلم
because then other insects bite that point.
لأن حشرات أخرى تقرص هذه المناطق.
And every year,
وفي كل عام،
99.9 percent of the paddy is transplanted manually.
99.9٪ من الأرز يزرع يدويًا.
No machines have been developed.
ورغم ذلك لم تصمم أي آلات لتقوم بهذا العمل.
So the silence of scientists,
لذا فصمت العلماء،
of technologists, of public policy makers,
والتكنولوجيين، والسياسيين،
of the change agent, drew our attention that this is not on, this is not on;
وقادة التغيير، جذب اهتمامنا، أن هذا النظام لا يعمل
this is not the way society will work.
ليست هذه هي الطريقة التي سيعمل بها المجتمع.
This is not what our parliament would do. You know,
ليس هذا ما سيقوم به البرلمان. تعرفون.
we have a program for employment:
لدينا برنامج للتوظيف.
One hundred, 250 million people
في هذا الإطار فإن 250 مليون نسمة
have to be given jobs for 100 days by this great country.
لابد أن توفر لهم وظائف خلال 100 يوم في هذا البلد العظيم.
Doing what? Breaking stones, digging earth.
ليقوما بماذا؟ تكسير الصخور وحفر الأرض.
So we asked a question to the parliament:
ولهذا سألنا البرلمان سؤالًا
Do poor have heads?
هل يمتلك الفقراء رؤوسًا؟
Do poor have legs, mouth and hands, but no head?
هل يمتلك الفقراء سيقانًا وأفواهًا وأيدي، ولكن لا رؤوس؟
So Honey Bee Network builds upon the resource in which poor people are rich.
تُبنى شبكة نحل العسل على الموارد التي يعتبر الشعب غني بها.
And what has happened?
ثم ماذا حدث؟
An anonymous, faceless, nameless person
شخص مجهول الشخصية والوجه والإسم
gets in contact with the network,
يحتك بهذه الشبكة
and then gets an identity.
ومن ثم يحصل على هوية.
This is what Honey Bee Network is about.
هذا هو ما تبنى عليه شبكة نحلات العسل.
And this network grew voluntarily,
وتنمو هذه الشبكة طواعية.
continues to be voluntary,
وتستمر في كونها للمتطوعين
and has tried to map the minds
وحاولت هذه الشبكة رسم خريطة لعقول
of millions of people
ملايين الناس
of our country and other parts of the world who are creative.
من بلادنا ومن أجزاء أخرى من العالم والذين أبدعوا.
They could be creative in terms of education,
الذين أبدعوا في التعليم؛
they may be creative in terms of culture,
أبدعوا في الثقافة
they may be creative in terms of institutions;
أبدعوا في المؤسسات
but a lot of our work is in the field of technological creativity,
ولكن الكثير من عملنا في الإبداع التكنولوجي،
the innovations,
الابتكارات
either in terms of contemporary innovations,
سواءًا من ناحية الابتكارات الحديثة،
or in terms of traditional knowledge.
أو من ناحية العلوم التقليدية.
And it all begins with curiosity.
وقد بدأ الأمر بالفضول
It all begins with curiosity.
فكل شيء يبدأ بالفضول.
This person, whom we met -- and you will see it on the website,
هذا الرجل الذي قابلناه، وسوف ترونه على الموقع الإليكتروني،
www.sristi.org -- this tribal person,
www.sristi.org ، هذا الرجل القَبَلي
he had a wish.
كانت لديه أمنية
And he said, "If my wish gets fulfilled" --
وقد قال، "لو تحققت أمنيتي" ---
somebody was sick and he had to monitor --
شخص ما كان مريضًا واضطر هو لمراقبته
"God, please cure him.
فقال "يارب، اشفه أرجوك،
And if you cure him, I will get my wall painted."
ولو شفيته، فسوف أرسم على حائط بيتي".
And this is what he got painted.
وهذا ما رسمه.
Somebody was talking yesterday about Maslowian hierarchy.
لقد تكلم أحدهم بالأمس عن هرمية "ماسلو" للإحتياجات البشرية
There could be nothing more wrong than
لا يوجد شئ أكثر خطأ من
the Maslowian model of hierarchy of needs
هرمية "مالسو" للإحتياجات البشرية
because the poorest people in this country can get enlightenment.
لأن الفقراء في هذا البلد يمتلكون البصيرة
Kabir, Rahim, all the great Sufi saints,
كبير، رحيم، وكل الحكماء الصوفيون،
they were all poor people,
كانو جميعًا فقراء،
and they had a great reason. (Applause)
وكانت عندهم حكمة عظيمة.
Please do not ever think that
أرجوكم لا تفكروا أبدًا أنه
only after meeting your physiological needs and other needs
فقط بعد أن تسدوا احتياجاتكم الفسيولوجية والاحتياجات الأخرى
can you be thinking about your spiritual needs or your enlightenment.
يمكنكم أن تفكروا في احتياجاتكم الروحانية وبصائركم.
Any person anywhere is capable
أي شخص في أي مكان يستطيع
of rising to that highest point of attainment,
أن يسمو إلى أعلى نقطة من بلوغ الهدف،
only by the resolve that they have in their mind that they must achieve something.
فقط بالتيقن الداخلي في عقله أنه لابد أن يحقق شيئًا ما.
Look at this.
انظروا إلى هذا.
We saw it in Shodh Yatra. Every six months we walk
لقد رأينا هذا في شوده ياترا . كل ستة أشهر نمشي
in different parts of the country.
في مناطق مختلفة من البلاد
I've walked about 4,000 kilometers in the last 12 years.
لقد مشيت أكثر من 4000 كيلومتر في الـ 12 عامًا الأخيرة
So on the wayside
وعلى جانب الطريق،
we found these dung cakes,
وجدنا هذه الأقراص من الروث،
which are used as a fuel.
والتي تستخدم كوقود.
Now, this lady, on the wall of the dung cake heap,
الآن، هذه السيدة، على حائط هذه الكومة من أقراص الروث
has made a painting.
قد رسمت لوحة
That's the only space she could express her creativity.
هذه هي المساحة الوحيدة التي استطاعت أن تعبر فيها عن إبداعاتها
And she's so marvelous.
وهي رائعة.
Look at this lady, Ram Timari Devi,
انظروا إلي هذه السيدة، رام تيماري ديفي،
on a grain bin. In Champaran, we had a Shodh Yatra
على مخزن حبوب في تشامباران، وكان لدينا شوده ياترا
and we were walking
وكنا نمشي
in the land where Gandhiji went
على الأرض التي ذهب إليها غاندي
to hear about the tragedy, pain
لنسمع عن الآلام والمآسي
of indigo growers.
التي عاناها زراع النيلة
Bhabi Mahato in Purulia and Bankura.
بابي ماهاتو في بورولينا في بانكورا
Look at what she has done.
انظر ما الذي فعلته.
The whole wall is her canvas. She's sitting there with a broom.
الحائط كله هو لوحتها. انها تجلس هناك ومعها مكنسة.
Is she an artisan or an artist?
هل هي حرفية أو فنانة؟
Obviously she's an artist; she's a creative person.
إنها فنانة بكل وضوح؛ انها انسانة مبدعة.
If we can create markets for these artists,
لو أمكننا خلق أسواق لهؤلاء الفنانين،
we will not have to employ them for digging earth and breaking stones.
فلن نضطر لتوظيفهم في حفر الأرض وتكسير الحجارة.
They will be paid for what they are good at, not what they're bad at.
سوف يؤجرون على ما يجيدونه، لا ما لا يجيدونه.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Look at what Rojadeen has done.
انظر ماذا فعل روجادين
In Motihari in Champaran,
في موتيهاري في تشاباران،
there are a lot of people who sell tea on the shack
هناك العديد من الناس الذين يبيعون الشاي في الأكشاك
and, obviously, there's a limited market for tea.
ويبدو واضحًا أن سوق الشاي محدود،
Every morning you have tea, as well as coffee.
كل صباح تشرب الشاي والقهوة.
So he thought, why don't I convert
لذا فقد فكر هو، لماذا لا أحول
a pressure cooker into a coffee machine?
قدر ضغط إلى ماكينة قهوة
So this is a coffee machine. Just takes a few hundred rupees.
هذه ماكينة قهوة، تكلفت بضعة مئات من الروبيات فقط
People bring their own cooker,
يحضر الناس قدور الضغط الخاصة بهم،
he attaches a valve and a steam pipe,
يركب هو لها صمام وانبوب بخار،
and now he gives you espresso coffee. (Laughter)
ويقدم لك قهوة اسبريسو
Now, this is a real, affordable
والآن، هذه ماكينة قهوة
coffee percolator that works on gas.
حقيقية ورخيصة وتعمل بالغاز.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Look at what Sheikh Jahangir has done.
انظر إلى ما فعله شيخ جاهانجير.
A lot of poor people do not have
لا يملك الكثير من الفقراء
enough grains to get ground.
الكمية الكافية من الحبوب ليمكن طحنها.
So this fellow is bringing
لذا أحضر صديقنا هذا
a flour-grinding machine on a two-wheeler.
ماكينة طحن الحبوب على عجلتين.
If you have 500 grams, 1000, one kilogram,
لو كان لديك 500 جرام أو كيلوجرام،
he will grind it for it for you; the flourmill will not grind such a small quantity.
سوف يطحنها لك؛ لان مطاحن الدقيق لن تقبل بهذه الكمية القليلة لتطحنها.
Please understand the problem of poor people.
أرجوكم افهموا مشكلة الفقراء.
They have needs which
إن لديهم احتياجات
have to be met efficiently
لابد من توفيرها بأقصى كفاءة ممكنة
in terms of energy, in terms of cost, in terms of quality.
من ناحية الطاقة والتكلفة والجودة.
They don't want second-standard, second-quality outputs.
انهم لا يريدون الدرجة الثانية من الجودة والمعايير.
But to be able to give them high-quality output
ولكن لتستطيع أن توفر لهم منتجات ذات جودة عالية.
you need to adapt technology to their needs.
لابد أن تسخر التكنولوجيا لاحتياجاتهم.
And that is what Sheikh Jahangir did.
وهذا ما فعله شيخ جاهانجير.
But that's not enough, what he did. Look at what he did here.
ولكن هذا لا يكفي، انظروا إلى ما فعله هنا.
If you have clothes, and you don't have enough time to wash them,
لو كانت لديك ملابس، وليس لديك الوقت الكافي لتغسلها،
he brought a washing machine
لقد أحضر ماكينة لغسل الملابس
to your doorstep, mounted on a two-wheeler.
حتى باب منزلك، مثبته على عجلات.
So here's a model where
فهاهو نموذج
a two-wheeler washing machine ...
لغسالة ملابس ذات عجلات
He is washing your clothes and drying them at your doorstep.
انه يغسل ملابسك ويجففها عند باب منزلك.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
You bring your water, you bring your soap,
انت تحضر الماء الخاص بك، وأنت تحضر الصابون.
I wash the clothes for you. Charge 50 paisa, one rupee
انا اغسل الملابس لك، وآخذ 50 بيسا أو روبية واحدة
for you per lot,
منك لكل مقدار من الغسيل.
and a new business model can emerge.
ويتمكن نوع جديد من الأعمال من الظهور.
Now, what we need is, we need
والآن، ما نحتاجه هو، نحتاج
people who will be able to scale them up.
أناس يستطيعون تنمية هذه الأعمال لأحجام أكبر.
Look at this.
انظروا إلى هذا.
It looks like a beautiful photograph.
انها تبدو كصورة جميلة.
But you know what it is? Can anybody guess what it is?
ولكن أتعرفون ما هي؟ هل يستطيع أحد أن يخبرني ما هي؟
Somebody from India would know, of course.
بالطبع أي أحد من الهند سوف يعلم، بالطبع.
It's a tawa.
إنها تاوا.
It's a hot plate made of clay.
انه طبق للطهي مصنوع من الطين.
Now, what is the beauty in it?
والآن ما هو الجمال فيها؟
When you have a non-stick pan,
عندما يكون عندك مقلاة غير قابلة للإلتصاق،
it costs about,
فإنها تتكلف حوالي
maybe, 250 rupees,
ربما، 250 روبية
five dollars, six dollars.
خمسة دولارات أو ستة
This is less than a dollar
ولكن هذه تكلف أقل من دولار واحد.
and this is non-stick;
وهي غير قابلة للإلتصاق أيضًا.
it is coated with one of these
إنها مغطاة بواحدة من هذه
food-grade materials.
المواد غير الضارة.
And the best part is that,
والجزء الأفضل هو أنك
while you use a costly non-stick pan,
أثناء استخدامك للمقلاة المكلفة غير القابلة للإلتصاق
you eat the so-called Teflon
فإنك تأكل التيفلون
or Teflon-like material
أو تلك المادة الشبيهة به -التي تمنع التصاق الطعام -
because after some time the stuff disappears. Where has it gone?
لأنه بعد فترة تختفي هذه المادة. إلى أين ذهبت؟
It has gone in your stomach. It was not meant for that. (Laughter)
ذهبت إلى معدتك. رغم انها لم تصمم لذلك .
You know? But here
انت تعلم، ولكن هنا
in this clay hot plate,
في هذا الطبق الطيني
it will never go into your stomach.
لن يذهب أبدًا إلى معدتك،
So it is better, it is safer;
ولهذا فهو أفضل، وأأمن؛
it is affordable, it is energy-efficient.
ورخيص؛ وكفء بيئيًا
In other words, solutions by the poor people need not be cheaper,
بمعنى آخر، ابتكارات الفقراء لا تحتاج أن تكون أرخص
need not be, so-called, jugaad, need not be some kind of makeshift arrangement.
ليست بالضرورة مركبات محلية الصنع ولا بالضرورة توظيفا متواضعا للموارد المتاحة.
They have to be better, they have to be more efficient,
لابد أن تكون أفضل، لابد أن تكون أكثر كفاءة،
they have to be affordable.
لابد أن تكون في متناول الجميع.
And that is what Mansukh Bhai Prajapati has done.
وهذا ما فعله منسوخ باي براجاباتي.
He has designed this plate with a handle.
لقد صمم هذا الطبق ذو اليد.
And now with one dollar,
والآن بدولار واحد،
you can afford a better alternative
يمكن أن تجد بديل أفضل
than the people market is offering you.
من المقلاة المكلفة المتوفرة في السوق.
This lady, she developed
هذه المرأة، لقد طورت
a herbal pesticide formulation.
صيغة عشبية لإبادة الحشرات
We filed the patent for her,
ولقد قدمنا للحصول لها على براءة اختراع،
the National Innovation Foundation.
من المؤسسة الوطنية للإبتكار.
And who knows? Somebody will license this technology
ومن يعلم، ربما يشتري أحد ما ترخيص هذه التكنولوجيا
and develop marketable products,
ويطور منها منتجات قابلة للتسويق،
and she would get revenue.
وسوف تنال هي عائد مالي يوما ما .
Now, let me mention one thing:
والآن، دعوني أذكر لكم شيئًا واحدًا.
I think we need a polycentric model of development,
أظننا نحتاج نموذج متعدد المراكز للتطوير،
where a large number of initiatives in different parts of the country,
حيث تظهر كمية كبيرة من المبادرات في مناطق مختلفة من البلاد،
in different parts of the world,
في مناطق مختلفة من العالم،
would solve the needs of locality
سوف تحل احتياجات المحلية
in a very efficient and adaptive manner.
بشكل شديد الكفاءة وله القدرة على التكيف.
Higher the local fit,
وترفع الكفاءة المحلية.
greater is the chance of scaling up.
وتزيد الفرصة للنمو،
In the scaling up,
وفي هذا النمو
there's an inherent inadequacy
هناك حاجة أساسية
to match the needs of the local people,
للوفاء باحتياجات السكان المحليين
point by point, with the supply that you're making.
ندا بند مع ما توفره أنت من هذه الاحتياجات
So why are people willing to adjust with that mismatch?
والآن لماذا يريد الناس التواؤم مع هذا؟
Things can scale up, and they have scaled up.
يمكن للأمور أن تنمو، وقد نمت بالفعل.
For example, cell phones: We have 400 million cellphones in this country.
مثلًا، الهواتف النقالة: لدينا 400 مليون جوال في هذه البلاد.
Now, it is possible that I use only two buttons on the cellphone,
والآن، قد استخدم زرين فقط في الهاتف النقال.
only three options on the cellphone.
فقط ثلاثة امكانيات في هذا الهاتف.
It has 300 options, I'm paying for 300; I'm using only three
ولكن هذا الهاتف يحتوي على 300 امكانية؛ وأنا أدفع ثمنها جميعًا؛ في حين أستعمل ثلاثة فقط،
but I'm willing to live with it, therefore it is scaling up.
ولكني أنوي التعايش مع هذا، ولهذا فهو قابل للنمو.
But if I had to get a match to match,
ولكن إذا اضطررت لجعله أكثر تلاؤما مع الاحتياجات،
obviously, I would need a different design of a cellphone.
فمن الواضح، أنني سأحتاج إلى تصميم آخر للهواتف النقالة.
So what we're saying is that scalability
لهذا ما أقوله هو أن النمو
should not become an enemy of sustainability.
لا ينبغي أن يكون عدو للإستدامة.
There must be a place in the world
لابد من وجود مكان ما في العالم.
for solutions that are only relevant for a locality,
ينتج حلولًا تتعلق فقط بمشكلات خاصة بإقليم معين،
and yet, one can be able to fund them.
ويمنحنا أيضًا القابلية لتمويلهم.
One of the greatest studies that we've been finding is
واحدة من أكثر الدراسات التي وجدناها هي
that many times investors would ask this question --
أن المستثمرون دائمًا ما يسألون هذا السؤال--
"What is a scalable model?" --
"ما هو النموذج القابل للنمو؟"--
as if the need of a community, which is only
كما لو كانت حاجة المجتمع الذي فقط
located in a space and time
يقع في مساحة وزمن معينين
and has those needs only located in those places,
واحتياجاته الخاصة ترتبط فقد بهذه المساحة الجغرافية،
has no legitimate right to get them for free
كما لو كان ليس لهم الحق المشروع في أن يحصلوا عليها مجانًا،
because it's not part of a larger scale.
لأنهم ليسوا جزءًا من شريحة أكبر.
So either you sub-optimize your needs to a larger scale
فأنت بحسب ذلك المفهوم اما تأقلم احتياجاتك مع ذلك " النموذج " المصنوع لغيرك - للشريحة التي اختارها المستثمرون
or else you remain out.
او انك تبقى خارج اللعبة - بدون استيفاء احتياجاتك
Now, the eminent model, the long-tail model
اليوم النموذج الأمثل، هو نموذج الذيل الطويل
tells you that small sales
يقول لك أن حتى المبيعات القليلة
of a large number of books, for example,
لعدد كبير من الكتب على سبيل المثال
having only a few copies sold
يباع منها نسخ قليلة فقط،
can still be a viable model.
يمكن أن يعد من النماذج القابلة للتطبيق.
And we must find a mechanism where
لذا يتوجب علينا ان نجد الآلية
people will pool in the portfolio, will invest in the portfolio,
التي تجعل الاشخاص يجتمعون معاً ويقدمون أفكارهم .. لكي نستثمر بها
where different innovations will go to
حيث سوف تخرج ابتكارات جديدة ومختلفة الى السطح
a small number of people in their localities,
من قبل اعداد صغيرة من الاشخاص ضمن مجتمعاتهم وتستهدف شريحة صغيرة ايضا
and yet, the overall platform of the model will become viable.
ورغم هذا سوف يعد " اختراعهم - نموذجهم " مناسب وبارز
Look at what he is doing.
انظروا ماذا فعل
Saidullah Sahib is an amazing man.
سعد الله صاحب هو رجل رائع جدا
At the age of 70,
في السبعون من عمره
he is linking up something very creative.
قدم شيئاً مبدعاً جداً
(Music)
(موسيقى)
Saidullah Sahib: I couldn't wait for the boat.
سعد الله صاحب : لايمكنني ان انتظر القارب
I had to meet my love.
علي أن أُلاقي حبيبتي
My desperation made me an innovator.
لقد قادني احباطي الى هذا الابداع
Even love needs help from technology.
حتى الحب يحتاج الى المساعدة من التكنولوجيا
Innovation is the light of my wife, Noor.
هذا الابتكار حق لزوجتي " نور "
New inventions are the passion of my life.
ان الاختراعات هوسي في هذه الحياة
My technology.
التكنولوجيا التي إخترعت !
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
AG: Saidulluh Sahib is
أنيل جوبتا : سعد الله صاحب من
in Motihari, again in Champaran.
موتيهاري أيضًا في شامباران
Wonderful human being,
رجلٌ رائعٌ جدا
but he stills sells, at this age,
وهو برغم عمره الكبير مازال يبيع
honey on a cycle to earn his livelihood,
العسل على دراجته الهوائية لكي يعيل نفسه
because we haven't been able to convince the water park people,
لاننا لم نستطع ان نقنع اصحاب الحدائق المائية
the lake people, in [unclear] operations.
او المسؤلين عن البحيرات .. او الشركات المتعلقة بها
And we have not been able to convince the fire brigade people
او الناس الذين يعملون مع لواء الاطفال
in Mumbai -- where there was a flood a few years ago
في مومباي بإعتماد هذا الاختراع .. حيث كان هنالك طوفان منذ عدة سنوات،
and people had to walk 20 kilometers, wading in the water --
وكان يتوجب على الناس السير 20 كم في المياه لكي يصلوا الى اعمالهم
that, look, you should have this cycle in your fire brigade office
وقلنا لهم ربما يتوجب عليكم شراء هذه الدراجة التي تسير على الماء
because you can then go to those lanes
لانه وبواسطتها يمكنكم الوصول الى القنوات والعبارات
where your buses will not go, where your transport will not go.
التي لن تستطيع عرباتكم الوصول اليها او نواقلكم
So we have not yet cracked the problem
إذن فنحن حتى الآن لم نتعامل مع مشكلة
of making it available as a rescue device,
أن نجعلها متاحة كعربة انقاذ
as a vending device during the floods in eastern India,
تستخدم اوقات الفياضانات في الهند الغربية
when you have to deliver things to people
حين يتوجب عليك ان تصل الى الاشخاص المعزولين
in different islands
في جزرهم
where they're marooned.
حيث انقطعت بهم السبل.
But the idea has a merit. The idea has a merit.
ولكن الفكرة مميزة .. ولكل فكرة تميزها
What has Appachan done? Appachan, unfortunately, is no more,
لنتحدث عن " أباشان " ماذا فعل .. والذي توفي منذ مدة للاسف
but he has left behind a message.
ولكنه ترك لنا رسالة
A very powerful message
قوية جدًا تقول
Appachan: I watch the world wake up every day.
أباشان : انا اشاهد الناس كل يوم تستيقظ من نومها
(Music)
(موسيقى)
It's not that a coconut fell on my head,
جوز الهند هذا لم يسقط من تلقاء نفسه
and I came upon this idea.
ولقد خطرت ببالي فكرة
With no money to fund my studies,
بدون ان املك اي تمويل لمخططاتي
I scaled new heights.
واليوم انا اصل الى ارتفاعات جديدة
Now, they call me the local Spiderman.
وهم يدعونني هنا " الرجل العنكبوت "
My technology.
التكنولوجيا التي إخترعت !
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
AG: Many of you
أنيل جوبتا : العديد منكم
might not realize and believe
ربما لن يستوعب او يصدق
that we have sold this product internationally --
اننا بعنا هذا النموذج عالميا
what I call a G2G model,
والذي ادعوه نموذج " g2g "
grassroots to global.
أي ما يعني "من الجذور الى العالمية "
And a professor in the University of Massachusetts,
وهنالك أستاذة في جامعة ماستوستش
in the zoology department,
متخصصة بعلم الحيوان
bought this climber because she wanted
اشترت هذه المتسلقة لانها كانت تريد
to study the insect diversity
ان تدرس التنوع الحشري
of the top of the tree canopy.
على قمم الاشجار
And this device makes it possible
وقد سهل هذا الجهاز الامر
for her to take samples from a larger number of palms,
لكي تأخذ عينات اكبر من قمم اشجار النخيل
rather than only a few,
بدلا من اخذ عينات قليلة
because otherwise she had to make a big platform
لانه بدون هذا الجهاز كان عليها ان تصنع قوالب كبيرة من الطوب
and then climb her [unclear] would climb on that.
بحيث يقوم طلبة البحث العاملين معها بتسلقها.
So, you know, we are advancing the frontiers of science.
وكما ترون ها نحن نساعد في تقدم آفاق العلم.
Remya Jose has developed ...
لقد طورت " ريما جوس "
you can go to the YouTube and find India Innovates
يمكنكم مشاهدة هؤلاء المخترعون الهنود على موقع " يو تيوب "
and then you will find these videos.
وسوف تشاهدون ملفات الفيديو الخاصة بهم
Innovation by her when she was in class 10th:
لقد طوت اختراعا عندما كانت في الصف العاشر
a washing machine-cum-exercising machine.
فقد حولت آلة غسل الى آلة رياضية .
Mr. Kharai who is a physically challenged person,
السيد خاراي والذي هو شخص معاق جسديا
one and a half foot height, only.
ويبلغ طوله قدم ونصف فقط
But he has modified a two-wheeler so that he can get autonomy
طور كرسي المقعدين بصورة ما تمكنه من الانتصاب
and freedom and flexibility.
والتحرك بكل حرية ومرونة
This innovation is from the slums of Rio.
وهذا الاختراع ظهر من مشردي مدينة "ريو"
And this person, Mr. Ubirajara.
هذا الشخص يدعى السيد " يوبياجارا "
We were talking about, my friends in Brazil,
وقد حدثني اصدقائي في البرازيل
how we scale up this model in China and Brazil.
عن كيفية نقل هذه الفكرة الى البرازيل .. والى الصين أيضا
And we have a very vibrant network in China, particularly,
وقد غدا لدينا شبكة نابضة بالحياة في الصين
but also emerging in Brazil and other parts of the world.
ونحن ننمو أيضا في البرازيل وفي مناطق اخرى في العالم
This stand on the front wheel, you will not find on any cycle.
في الصورة ترون المقعد على العجلة الامامية .. وهو أمر لن تروه على أي دراجة هوائية
India and China have the largest number of cycles.
للعلم، الهند والصين بهما أكبر عدد مستخدمين للدراجات الهوائية
But this innovation emerged in Brazil.
ولكن هذا الاختراع ظهر في البرازيل
The point is, none of us should be parochial,
لذا يجب ان نكون واعين لنقطة مهمة وهي ان لا نكون " أحادي النظر "
none of us should be so nationalistic to believe
ولا يجب ان نكون عنصريون لهوياتنا
that all good ideas will come only from our country.
بأن نقول بأن كل الافكار الجيدة مصدرها دولتنا " الهند "
No, we have to have the humility to learn
لا، إن علينا أن نتحلى بالتواضع للتعلم
from knowledge of economically poor people, wherever they are.
من معارف الفقراء في كل مكان
And look at this whole range of cycle-based innovations:
انظروا الى هذا الاختراعات الكثيرة القائمة على الدراجات الهوائية
cycle that's a sprayer, cycle that
دراجات ترش المحاصيل .. وأخرى
generates energy from the shocks on the road.
تكتسب طاقة بسبب الاهتزازات على الطرق
I can't change the condition of the road,
فان لم استطع ان احسن حالة الطريق
but I can make the cycle run faster.
يمكنني ان استفيد منها بان اكسب دراجتي الهوائية طاقة لكي تسير اسرع
That is what Kanak Das has done.
وهذا ما قام به كاناكداس.
And in South Africa,
وفي جنوب افريقيا
we had taken our innovators,
أخذنا المخترعين
and many of us had gone there share with the colleagues in South Africa
معنا لكي يتشاركوا افكارهم مع زملائهم في جنوب افريقيا
as to how innovation can become
عن كيف يمكن للابتكار
a means of liberation
أن يصبح وسيلة للتحرر
from the drudgery that people have.
من العمل الروتيني الشاق الذي يقوم به الناس.
And this is a donkey cart which they modified.
وهذه العربة التي تجرها الحمير تم تعديلها
There's an axle here, of 30, 40 kg,
بحيث تم إلغاء محور بوزن 30 إلى 40 كغ
serving no purpose.
كان لا يفيد بشيء
Remove it, the cart needs one donkey less.
وبإزالته أصبحت العربة يمكن جرها بحمار أقل
This is in China. This girl needed a breathing apparatus.
وهذه الصورة من الصين . كانت هذه الفتاة تحتاج جهاز تنظيم تنفس
These three people in the village
وكان هنالك 3 أشخاص في القرية
sat down and decided to think,
جلسوا وفكروا،
"How do we elongate the life of this girl of our village?"
كيف يمكننا ان نطيل عمر هذه الفتاة ابنة هذه القرية ؟
They were not related to her, but they tried to find out,
دون ان يكون هنالك صلة قرابة بينهم .. ولكنهم حاولوا أن يكتشفوا طريقة ما
"How can we use ... "
باستخدام أنبوب آلة غسل ملابس
They used a cycle, they put together a breathing apparatus.
واستخدموا عجلة هوائية .. وقاموا بصنع جهاز تنفس
And this breathing apparatus now saved the life,
مما أدى الى إنقاذ حياة هذه الفتاة
and she's very welcome.
على الرحب والسعة.
There's a whole range of innovations that we have.
ونحن نملك طيف كبير من الاختراعات
A car, which runs on compressed air
كسيارة تسير على الهواء المضغوط
with six paisa per kilometer.
بتكلفة ستة بيسة لكل كيلو متر
Assam, Kanak Gogoi.
آسام، كانك جوجي .
And you would not find this car in U.S. or Europe,
ولن تجد هذه السيارة .. في الولايات المتحدة او اوروبا
but this is available in India.
ولكنك ستجدها في الهند
Now, this lady, she used to do the winding of the yarn
والآن هذه السيدة والتي تقوم بتصفية الخيوط المغزولة
for Pochampally Saree.
للباس الساري ببوشامبالي.
In one day, 18,000 times,
18000 مرة في يوم واحد
she had to do this winding
وتقوم بهذه التصفية
to generate two sarees.
لكي تصنع ساريين
This is what her son has done after seven years of struggle.
وهذا ما صنعه ابنها بعد سبع سنوات من المعاناة
She said, "Change your profession."
قالت " قم بتغيير مهنتك."
He said, "I can't. This is the only thing I know, but I'll invent a machine,
فقال " لا يمكنني أن أغير هذه المهنة لأنها الوحيدة التي أعرف .. ولكني سوف أخترع آلة
which will solve your problem."
ستحل مشكلتك."
And this is what he did, a sewing machine in Uttar Pradesh.
وهذا ما قام به، ماكينة خياطة في مدينة " آتر براديش "
So, this is what SRISTI is saying:
وهذا ما قاله" سريستي "
"Give me a place to stand, and I will move the world."
" اعطني مكانك لكي اقف فيه .. وسوف احرك العالم كما اريد "
I will just tell you that we are also doing a competition among children
اريد ان اقول لكم اننا ايضا ننظم مسابقة بين الاطفال
for creativity, a whole range of things.
عن الابداع .. وعن كل تلك الاختراعات والافكار
We have sold things all over the world,
ومن ثم نقوم ببيع هذه الافكار الى العالم
from Ethiopia to Turkey to U.S. to wherever.
من أثيوبيا الى تركيا الى الولايات المتحدة الامريكية والى كل بقعة في الارض
Products have gone to the market, a few.
وقد وصلت بعض المنتجات الى الاسواق العالمية
These are the people whose knowledge made
هؤلاء هم الاشخاص الذين صنعت أفكارهم
this Herbavate cream for eczema possible.
هذا المرهم العشبي الذي جعل حل مشكلة الإكزما ممكناً
And here, a company which licensed this herbal pesticide
وهنا شركة قامت بترخيص هذا المبيد الحشري العشبي
put a photograph of the innovator on the packing
وضعت صورة المبتكر على علبة ذلك المنتج
so that every time a user uses it,
بحيث يكون في كل مرة يستخدمه فيها المستخدم
it asks the user, "You can also be an innovator.
كأنما المنتج يشجعه "أنت أيضًا يمكن أن تكون مبتكرًا"
If you have an idea, send it back to us."
إذا كنت تملك فكرة أرسلها لنا "
So, creativity counts, knowledge matters,
لذا فالابداع يحسب .. والمعرفة تفيد
innovations transform, incentives inspire.
والاختراعات تتحول وتنتشر .. والحوافز تُلهم
And incentives: not just material, but also non-material incentives.
والحوافز ليست مادية فحسب .. بل هنالك حوافز معنوية كثيرة جدا !
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
تصفيق